The women told me, "You'll adjust to this place. You'll fit right in." I was no longer referred to as Teresa Njoroge. The number 415/11 was my new identity, and I soon learned that was the case with the other women who we were sharing this space with. And adjust I did to life on the inside: the prison food, the prison language, the prison life. Prison is certainly no fairytale world. What I didn't see come my way was the women and children whom we served time and shared space with, women who had been imprisoned for crimes of the system, the corruption that requires a fall guy, a scapegoat, so that the person who is responsible could go free, a broken system that routinely vilifies the vulnerable, the poorest amongst us, people who cannot afford to pay bail or bribes. And so we moved on. As I listened to story after story of these close to 700 women during that one year in prison, I soon realized that crime was not what had brought these women to prison, most of them, far from it.
Las mujeres me dijeron, "Te adaptarás a este lugar. Te acostumbrarás". Ya no me llamaban Teresa Njoroge. El número 415/11 era mi nueva identidad, y pronto aprendí que ese era el caso de otras mujeres con quién compartía ese espacio. Y me adapté a la vida tras las rejas: la comida de la prisión, el idioma de la prisión, la vida de la prisión. La prisión ciertamente no es un mundo de cuento de hadas. Lo que no comprendo es la manera como mujeres y niños con quien compartí tiempo y espacio, habían sido encarceladas por crímenes del sistema, por una corrupción que requiere un culpable, un chivo expiatorio, para que la persona responsable quede libre, un sistema roto que rutinariamente vilipendia a los vulnerables, a los más pobres de nosotros, personas que no pueden pagar la fianza o los sobornos. Y así continuamos. Mientras escuchaba historia tras historia de estas casi 700 mujeres durante ese año en prisión, pronto me di cuenta de que el crimen no fue lo que llevó a estas mujeres a prisión, a la mayoría de ellas, ni muchos menos.
It had started with the education system, whose supply and quality is not equal for all; lack of economic opportunities that pushes these women to petty survival crimes; the health system, social justice system, the criminal justice system. If any of these women, who were mostly from poor backgrounds, fall through the cracks
Todo había comenzado con el sistema educativo, cuyo suministro y calidad no es igual para todos; la falta de oportunidades económicas empuja a estas mujeres a crímenes de supervivencia menores; el sistema de salud, sistema de justicia social, el sistema de justicia penal. Si alguna de estas mujeres, que eran en su mayoría de origen pobre, caen por las grietas
in the already broken system, the bottom of that chasm is a prison, period. By the time I completed my one-year sentence at Langata Women Maximum Prison,
del sistema en sí ya roto, el fondo de ese abismo es una prisión, punto. Cuando completé mi sentencia de un año en la prisión de mujeres de Langata,
I had a burning conviction to be part of the transformation to resolve the injustices that I had witnessed of women and girls who were caught up in a revolving door of a life in and out of prison due to poverty. After my release, I set up Clean Start. Clean Start is a social enterprise that seeks to give these women and girls a second chance. What we do is we build bridges for them. We go into the prisons, train them, give them skills, tools and support to enable them to be able to change their mindsets, their behaviors and their attitudes. We also build bridges into the prisons from the corporate sector -- individuals, organizations
tuve una convicción ardiente de ser parte de la transformación para resolver las injusticias de las que yo había sido testigo a mujeres y a niñas que fueron atrapadas en una puerta giratoria de una vida dentro y fuera de la prisión debido a la pobreza. Después de mi puesta en libertad, puse en marcha Clean Start. Clean Start es una empresa social que busca dar a estas mujeres y niñas una segunda oportunidad. Tendemos puentes para ellas. Entramos en las prisiones, las entrenamos, les damos habilidades, herramientas y apoyo para permitirles cambiar su forma de pensar, sus comportamientos y sus actitudes. También tendemos puentes hacia las cárceles desde el sector corporativo. Individuos, organizaciones
that will partner with Clean Start
que se asocian con Clean Start
to enable us to provide employment, places to call home, jobs, vocational training, for these women, girls,
para permitirnos proporcionar empleo, espacios a los que llamar hogar, trabajos y entrenamiento vocacional para estas mujeres, niñas,
boys and men, upon transition back into society. I never thought that one day I would be giving stories of the injustices that are so common within the criminal justice system, but here I am. Every time I go back to prison, I feel a little at home, but it is the daunting work to achieve the vision that keeps me awake at night, connecting the miles to Louisiana, which is deemed as the incarceration capital of the world, carrying with me stories of hundreds of women whom I have met within the prisons, some of whom are now embracing their second chances, and others who are still on that bridge of life's journey. I embody a line from the great Maya Angelou. "I come as one, but I stand as 10,000." (Applause) For my story is singular, but imagine with me the millions of people in prisons today, yearning for freedom. Three years post my conviction and two years post my release, I got cleared by the courts of appeal of any wrongdoing. (Applause) Around the same time, I got blessed with my son, whom I named Uhuru, which in my dialect means "freedom." (Applause) Because I had finally gotten the freedom
niños y hombres, desde la transición de vuelta a la sociedad. Nunca pensé que un día estaría narrando historias de las injusticias que son tan comunes dentro del sistema de la justicia penal, pero aquí estoy. Cada vez que vuelvo a la prisión, me siento un poco en casa, pero es el trabajo desalentador de lograr la visión lo que me mantiene despierta por la noche, lo que me conecta con Louisiana, considerada la capital mundial del encarcelamiento, llevando conmigo historias de cientos de mujeres a quienes he conocido dentro de las prisiones, algunas de las cuales ahora tienen su segunda oportunidad, y otras que todavía están en el camino del transcurso de la vida. Yo encarno una frase de la gran Maya Angelou. "Vengo sola, pero soy como 10 000". (Aplausos) Porque mi historia es singular, pero imaginen junto a mí los millones de personas en las cárceles de hoy, que anhelan libertad. Tres años después de mi condena y dos años tras mi puesta en libertad, los tribunales de apelación me dejaron libre de cualquier cargo. (Aplausos) Casi al mismo tiempo, fui bendecida con mi hijo, a quien llamé Uhuru, que en mi dialecto significa "libertad". (Aplausos) Porque finalmente había obtenido la libertad
that I so longed for. I come as one, but I stand as 10,000, encouraged by the hard-edged hope that thousands of us have come together to reform and transform the criminal justice system, encouraged that we are doing our jobs as we are meant to do them. And let us keep doing them with no apology. Thank you. (Applause)
que tanto anhelaba. Vengo sola, pero soy como 10 000 alentada por la dura esperanza de que miles de nosotras nos hemos reunido para reformar y transformar el sistema de justicia penal, alentadas por hacer nuestro trabajo como estamos destinadas a hacerlo. Y sigamos haciéndolo sin pedir disculpas. Gracias. (Aplausos)